<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciae veritatis a narrative vindicating the truth against the invective, malicious, and slanderous back-biting aspersions of certain non-conformists in and about London passing under the notions of Presbyterians, and others their pupils and confederates concerning the truths published in my Little book of the covenants and The personal reign of Christ ... / by the author John Humphryes.</title>
            <author>Humphreys, John, b. 1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10745787</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10745787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1405:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciae veritatis a narrative vindicating the truth against the invective, malicious, and slanderous back-biting aspersions of certain non-conformists in and about London passing under the notions of Presbyterians, and others their pupils and confederates concerning the truths published in my Little book of the covenants and The personal reign of Christ ... / by the author John Humphryes.</title>
                  <author>Humphreys, John, b. 1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45624:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45624:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VINDICIAE VERITATIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A NARRATIVE Vindicating the TRUTH, againſt The Invective, Malicious, and Slanderous Back-biting Aſperſions of certain NON-CONFORMISTS In, and about <hi>LONDON,</hi> Paſſing under the Notion of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and others their Pupils and Confederates, concerning the Truths publiſhed in my little Book of the <hi>Covenants,</hi> and the <hi>Perſonal Reign of Chriſt,</hi> lately Printed for Mr. <hi>Thomas Paſham</hi> in <hi>Fleet-lane;</hi> as alſo their abuſing me in their <hi>Synodical Seſſions</hi> at the <hi>Spittle</hi> and elſewhere, calling and whiſpering me to the World, to be a Jeſuit, and a Papiſt, and attempting to ſilence me, as well as my Book; becauſe of their Avaritious Intereſt of accumulating the Peoples Charity to themſelves, under pretence of caring for their Souls, and keeping them from Errours. And becauſe I refuſe to take my Meaſures from their <hi>Arminian, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi> Claſſes. Publiſhed to prevent the Jealouſies of the Godly in <hi>London,</hi> as alſo the Abuſe of the Truths of Chriſt, and further my own Liberty, Life, and Reputation; for the Churches and Goſpels ſake.</p>
            <p>By the Author <hi>JOHN H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHRYES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Veſtri fratres odio habentes vos, elongantes vos, propter Nomen meum, dixerunt, glorioſus fit Dominus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Brethren that hated you for my Names ſake, caſt you out, (or ſaid, Stand farther off us) and ſaid, The Lord be glorified in what we do.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.5. <hi>Mont.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſequium amicos, Veritas odium parit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Flattery gets Friends, and Truth gets Foes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the 9th. 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45624:2"/>
            <head>A Word to the Chriſtian Intelligent Reader.</head>
            <p>IN ſhort, I am traduced for a Jeſuit, who have taken my ſelf this twenty years to be the greateſt Antipapiſt in the World; Who my Accuſers are originally, I cannot tell, they that have thus aſperſed me, have made me the worſt of Mankind. Reader, doſt thou know a Jeſuit? Let me give thee ſome real Marks of a real Jeſuit, though 'tis hard to do in this Age, yet poſſible.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> A Jeſuit is one bred up properly in <hi>Jeſus-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> a place I never ſaw in all my Life.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> They are brought up to ſome Trade or other, that they may the better inſinuate their Errours; this I confeſs I had never the Happineſs to be of, and ſo the more uncapable of gaining a Living in theſe hard Times; though St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a Tent-maker as well as a Civilian.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> a Jeſuit is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſhaved on the Crown, 'tis true I have a Periwig, and but little Hair on my Crown, but yet I was never ſhaven there.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> A Jeſuit will not, cannot preach up the free Grace of God, but he muſt hang his Pipes on ſome Arminian String, by propping up the Creature in ſome Power that in his fallen State he hath not, or elſe when he tells you of Chriſts Merits, he minces them, and tells you, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs and Holineſs is by the Spirit communicated into us, and to our Nature infuſed, like the Hereſie of old <hi>Oſyander,</hi> honeſt <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaks of; but he will as ſoon be hanged at <hi>Tyborn,</hi> as to confeſs that it is the very Righteouſneſs and Holineſs that Chriſt as Mediator God-man, wrought in this individual Perſon, is by an Act of Grace given, and by Promiſe imputed to us, and received by Faith alone, without Works wrought in us or by us. And he cannot tell, that Faith and Repentance, and new Obedience are Fruits and Effects of our free Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification; but he will readily tell you, that they are Cauſes and Acts of ours preceding it or Conditions of it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> He is a met amorphoſied Creature, now a Quaker, now a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, now a Church of <hi>England</hi> man, a Baptiſt, finally, any thing but a true Evangeliſt, and that he can as ſoon be hanged as be, he can pretend to outward Phariſaical Holineſs well enough; and ſays, 'tis of the Spirit, yea he can be a Separatiſt too, but to believe that Jeſus in his Perſon and in his Room and Stead, did all for him as to his Righteouſneſs before God, this he cannot ſwallow: he is an old Phariſee in a finical, ſpiritual, pretended new Dreſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6.</hi> He allows lying with other mens Wives, if they pleaſe him, and calls Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Fornication but a venial Sin: and when his Luſt is hot, and the Creature weak and tender of Conſcience, 'tis no Sin at all.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7.</hi> No Creature hath more Confidence, even to the Extremity of Impudence than he, for if it be but for papal Intereſt, he can Murder, Regiſcide, or commit any horrid Act, with the Confidence of meriting Salvation thereby, yea he can look another mans Wife in the Face, and demand a Nights Lodging of her, and if ſhe deny him, and detect him, he can as confidently put it off with a Jeſt, as if he meant no ſuch thing really: All his Confeſſees are his Children, but eſpecially if they be of the Foeminine Gender.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8.</hi> He is very demure, when he is about his ſpiritual Concerns, but take him at another time, he's as apt to ſtumble at a Curtizens Lintel, and at a Firkin, if he miſs the Tavern, as any man living.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9.</hi> He is very zealous of obeying his Superiour, and makes it the chiefeſt Article of his Creed, to be very obedient to them, whilſt in the Method and Courſe of his Life, he horridly violates the Command of God. <hi>Q.</hi> Whether ſome that look for Attention from others like <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> be not infected with the Itch of the Jeſuits?</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10.</hi> He hates Marriage (and living with a Wife) as his Maſter does Holy-water, but a Whore is the beſt ſpoke in's Cart at ſome times.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel,</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45624:2"/>
            <head>VINDICIAE VERITATIS.</head>
            <p>IT was the frequent Cry of the <hi>Jews</hi> of old, in their greateſt Diſcrtions from God and his Covenant, <hi>The Temple of the Lord,</hi> the Temple of the Lord; thereby thinking to blind the World and their Conſciences with their outward formal Services and ignorant Zeal, while they and their Children made Cakes and offered them to the Queen of Heaven, and were found treading the Steps of Idolators, proud Boaſters, fiery Zealots, Oppreſſors, Covetous, Proud, hating and perſecuting all that did not pin their Faith on their Sleeves, and draw their Meaſures from their Lines; though never ſo corrupt and falſe. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7.8, 9, 10.18. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.20, 21. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 20.10.11. Of the ſame Spirit were the Scribes and Phariſees in our Lords Days, and the furious zealous <hi>Jews</hi> in the Apoſtles times. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.5, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. and to the end. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. And of the ſame Stamp are many of our zealous and <hi>Jehu</hi>-like Presbyterians, in this our day, who would truly have done the Church of Chriſt more Service, and the Lord leſs Diſhonour, if they had upon their black <hi>Bartholomew</hi> day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the preſent times; and he that varies from me in this Particular, either like the Mole is blind, or elſe like a K. is a Reſpector of mens Perſons. The Holy, humble, tender hearted and truly evangelically principled, that have the Apoſtles Spirit, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.14.15. by what ever Names they are called or diſtinguiſh'd, I truly honour them, and love them with my whole Soul.<note place="margin">Quid verba au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam cum facta videam.</note> Neither would I have attempted this Vindication, but that, not only to the Loſs of my Reputation by calling me Antinomian, but to my Life and Liberty, by calling me a Jeſuit, and that in ſuch a time when ſo many of that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction have been found plotting the Nations Ruin, and the Kings Majeſties Life. Had not their Envy ſtruck alſo (though moſt falſely and inteſtinely malicious) at my Life, and the Honour of the Goſpel, of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Sardis me auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus accepiſſe niſi propter verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Riv. Epiſt. ad Balſac.</note> I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly would have paſſed all by in Silence, which now I publiſh to the World for the ſake of well minded Chriſtians, and the Intereſt of Chriſt. Even ſo many of ours cry out, the Goſpel the Goſpel, and teach their Pupills to paratize like <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Parrot, that could cry out nothing but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God ſave <hi>Caeſar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo theſe can cry nothing but <hi>Our Goſpel Miniſters, our Goſpel Miniſters,</hi> like Parrots that ſpeak by Roat, what they are taught: when theſe Diſciples truly, (unleſs they have learned their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm by Head) can ſay nothing by Experience or by Heart; for their Teachers are truly nothing leſs, in both Principle and Life, having no more Love in their Lives, than the Scribes and Phariſees had, who gilded the Sepulchres of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45624:3"/>whom their Fathers killed, whoſe Writings and Preachments are filled up with as bad Doctrine, and as like as an Apple to a Pomewater, as any is in <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Scotus, Aquinas, Huberus, Hemingius</hi> or any of the Jeſuits and Papiſts, yet I will not betray my Folly to ſay they are Papiſts, or my Knavery to ſay they are Jeſuits; but this I think of them, that they ignorantly like the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, teach and preach Popery and write it, becauſe they know not the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4. and herein their Pride alſo appears, becauſe they hate all that differ or diſſent from their falſe Principles,<note place="margin">Hugo Grotius Papizat. ſic ejus Diſcipuli.</note> founding themſelves upon Arminiaſniſm, Grotianiſm, and Papiſm, rather pinning their Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Faith upon mens humane Arguments, than the pure infallible Word of God, which is able to cut and hamſtring all their Sophiſtry and falſe Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. though guarded with the dialectical Spears of <hi>Aquinas, Scotus</hi> or all the Popiſh Schoolmen; as <hi>Rivetus</hi> in his Epiſt. to Prince <hi>Frederick,</hi> in Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Goſpel againſt the Jeſuits. <hi>Gladium verbi Divini tractent cujus aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em merito reformidant, unde eſt quodicam retundere conantur excogitatis varii generis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phismatibus quibus incautos deripiunt.</hi> And I do the more wonder that I who have publiſhed my ſelf to the World by two or three Tracts in open Hoſtility againſt the Doctrine of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> and alſo <hi>Socinians,</hi> and plainly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered my ſelf to the World to be ſo great an <hi>Anti-arminian, Papiſt, Socinian,</hi> ſhould be by theſe Goſpel Miniſters called a Jeſuit; eſpecially when I conſider, that in the Writings of ſome worthy men, who like <hi>James, Cephas,</hi> and <hi>John, Gal.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. are ſuppoſed to be Pillars; there is ſo much ſtuff as like Popiſh Doctrine, as an <hi>Italian</hi> is like a <hi>Roman</hi> born; and yet, which adds to my Admiration, their Readers, and Hearers, admires them with as great Confidence, as if <hi>Paul</hi> were preaching, or they were reading one of his Epiſtles. My Proof for what I now ſay, ſhall be notorious,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Baxters Saints <hi>Reſt.</hi> part <hi>3.</hi> chap <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>270.</hi>
               </note> And this is the Doctrine that all men may be ſaved if they will, and then I am ſure, that all men are not dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. as the Apoſtle affirms, and the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalms</hi> 110.3. that Gods People even the Elect, are not a willing People, till by his Power he makes them ſo. And that Teſtimony of <hi>Jerem</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>V. My People are wife to do Evil, but to do Good they have no Knowledge.</hi> But may be, ſome may credit Mr. <hi>B.</hi> before the Apoſtle and the Prophet, or take his Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation before the plain Words of Scripture.<note n="‖" place="margin">Part <hi>3.</hi> chap. <hi>11.</hi> Sect. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>445.</hi>
               </note> And in the ſame Chapter, that infallible Knowledge is not a Certainty of Faith, now if Gods Promiſe to a Sinner be infallible, then may a Sinner by Faith infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly know it, as <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>&amp; Rev.</hi> 22.17. as his Portion. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> can ſay, nor does ſay no more than Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in the ſame place ſays, that he likes <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the Better. You may if you will hang your Faith on Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Sleeve, but I will not, ſo long as Gods Word is unburnt; and in the ſame Chapter, he playes the <hi>Arminian</hi> neatly, and in the laſt Sheet of the Book, by affirming that common Grace in all men, and ſpecial Grace in the regenerate, differs not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally (or phyſically) as he ſaid, but by a moral Specification, that is in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45624:3"/>Degree. And he ſays, that Divines make ſpecial Grace to lye in four things;
<list>
                  <item>1. The Love of God, whereby the Redeemer, Juſtifies, Elects, and Saves, theſe being immanent Acts in God, as the Means extended for all to have the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, if they will.</item>
                  <item>2. The Spirits act working and infuſing the ſaving Act into the Soul or habitual Acts, called <hi>Gratia Operans.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The Effects of the Spirits work the new Creature, the Seed remaining or real Holineſs.</item>
                  <item>4. The Exerciſe of theſe Habits, and in it lies the Queſtion about the Sincerity of Grace, and the Difference between common and ſpecial Grace, being as he ſaith, in the Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Degree, that is not Quality but Quantity.</item>
               </list> No Divines but Papiſts, <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Grotians,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> ever held this <hi>Phaenomena</hi> in Divinity except him. So that men may be elected, loved of God, juſtified, redeemed, and the Spirit may apply and infuſe Habits and Diſpoſitions at leaſt, and a new Creature may be regenerated; and yet in the Acts and Exerciſe of theſe Habits, there be not a Comparative Degree of Excellency, that man may be an Hypocrite; ſo then God may Love, Juſtifie, and Redeem Hypocrites. Did ever <hi>Bellarmine</hi> or any of the Schoolmen or Jeſuitical Tribe, ever ſpeak more to the Purpoſe, ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>chap.</hi> 11. and <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. beſide <hi>Aug. lib. de fide. chap.</hi> 14. <hi>Bona Opera ſequuntur juſtificatum non precedunt Juſtificandum,</hi> Good works follow a Perſon Juſtified, as Fruits and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is an Act of free Grace, that whoever hath it, cannot periſh, and by Faith alone it is received, and not by Love or any other Grace. The Juſt ſhall live by Faith, not any other Grace, though other Graces as Love <hi>&amp;c.</hi> follow true Faith. And (<hi>quomodo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rivet. qui vitam non habet poteſt operari?</hi>) who can work that hath no Life. The Tryal of the Sincerity and Truth of our Grace ſhould be placed in the Love of God, and Acts of free Grace by him in Chriſt, and tendred in the Promiſes and received by Faith. For Grace is ſavingly true, though it may not grow: as ſaid <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. why then ſhould Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> place the ſincere Degree in the Quantity and Exerciſe, and Growth of Grace?</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Frendeat uſque licet <hi>Satanas</hi> &amp; dira minetur,</l>
                  <l>Terreat inferni conſcia corda metu.</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nica Juſtificat nitens in ſanguine Chriſti,</l>
                  <l>Fructibus ipſa ſuis juſtificata fides.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Satan</hi> his helliſh Tooth doth gnaſh,</l>
                  <l>And when Fear of Hell the wounded Conſcience laſh,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Faith alone, in his Blood Juſtifies,</l>
                  <l>And Fruits of Love to men it verifies.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>And the Power of the Goſpel conſiſts not in the Fruits of Faith, but in Faith it ſelf. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.7. <hi>John</hi> 6.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.24. <hi>&amp;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45624:4"/>20.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13 5.<note place="margin">Dominus per Evangelium nos vocat, nos vocanti per fidem reſpondemus, <hi>Calv.</hi> fides propria eſt per quam obeditur Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, ut fide obediant Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelio bomines. <hi>Mela.</hi> on <hi>Rom. 1.5.</hi>
               </note> The Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Goſpel conſiſts in believing in the Son for our Juſtification and Sanctification too, yea for all without us and within us. By the Goſpel we are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by Faith we are ſure, not by Works faith Reverend <hi>Calvin,</hi> Faith is that properly by which we obey the Goſpel, ſaith <hi>Mela,</hi> and not works at all. And ſaith <hi>Brentius,</hi> unto Juſtification and Salvation no Work is required of God from us, except Faith alone in Jeſus Chriſt; yet Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in the ſame Chapter tells you, that no man can be juſtified before certain Acts and Conditions performed by the Creature. I will not ſay, this is Popery in a Fryers weed,<note place="margin">Ad Juſtitiam &amp; Salutem pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum nullum opus, aliud efflagitat. Deus praeterque fidem Jolam in Jeſu Chriſto in <hi>Joh,</hi>
               </note> but I am ſure, 'tis Popery in a Presbyterians weed, which I am ſorry for. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith alſo in the ſame Chapter, that a Woman may love her Husband, and yet proſtitute her ſelf to twenty other men, and her Love in the Sincerity of it differs not in the natural Act but Degree Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, whether ſhe love her Husband or theſe men more. And firſt, I think ſuch kind of Creatures would be beholding to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> if he can perſwade their Husbands,<note place="margin">If any object, why I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things, now let them know, that for theſe Abuſes of the Grace of God in Chriſt, all theſe Miſeries now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent and hanging o're ours, and the Nations Head; becauſe we have corrupted the pure Goſpel of Chriſt, by immixing Popiſh Errours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pretence of Piety and Holineſs.</note> that they may love them truly, and yet play the Whore with others. Beſides, this is ſuch Divinity that is fitter for a Curtizans Intrigue, than a Chriſtian Commonwealth. Now If I ſhould hold and defend ſuch Errours, it would be Hereſie in me, but I dare not ſay 'tis ſo in Mr. <hi>B.</hi> becauſe ſome men may break an Houſe, before ſome may draw the Latch.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give the World an Accout of
<list>
                  <item>1. my Birth and Breeding, Negative and Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative.</item>
                  <item>2. Of my Religion.</item>
                  <item>3. Of my coming up to <hi>London,</hi> and preſent Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Affairs.</item>
                  <item>4. As touching the Objection againſt my Book.</item>
                  <item>5. My Reaſons for my Non-appearance before certain Miniſters.</item>
                  <item>6. The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I was born of honeſt Parents, in the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Neen Savage, Anno Dom.</hi> 1637 brought up there; and in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Schools all my Days: and to ſome competent Degrees in Learning attained, but through the late Civil Wars, my Friends being impoveriſhed, and my Studies were prohibited. I never was in any Popiſh Dominions, nor in <hi>France, Spain, Italy,</hi> or <hi>Germany</hi> in all my Life.</p>
            <p>About eighteen years of Age, I went a Voyage into the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and being ſomewhat more than twenty years old, was ordained in <hi>Litchfield,</hi> to the Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Miniſtry. My whole Life was given to Study; in the days of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority I attained to ſome Knowledge in the Tongues, but being kept ſhort of this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45624:4"/>Worlds Good, could not attain to that Perfection I aimed at. In the further Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of my days, I addicted my ſelf to the Study, of ſome parts of Philoſophy, <hi>Mathematicks</hi> and <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> to <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and unto <hi>Divinity,</hi> in all which I confeſs my Ignorance too too much, and bewail that I have not been more laborious being ſubject to the <hi>Engliſh-man</hi>'s Humour, to be <hi>aliquid in ſingulis, ſed nihil in toto.</hi> 2. As to my Religion, I was never a Papiſt, but my Friends being of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Proteſtant Profeſſion, I was the ſame, <hi>de forma,</hi> in which I was bred; till about twenty years of Age, and a little more, God in infinite Mercy convinced me of Sin, and Wrath, and Hell, and ſo I was many Months in a deſpairing State, till he ſhewed me by his Grace, my Intereſt in the Blood of Chriſt, and gave me Faith to enclaſp about him; ſince which, I humbly confeſs I have diſhonoured his Name many ways, but yet throw Grace, beleive, I ſhall not be totally caſt off, becauſe he hath loved me with an everlaſting Love. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. <hi>So by his Grace, I am what I am now. Gal. 2. ult.</hi> I have been a Chaplain to the Lord <hi>Ward,</hi> dead long ſince, and to a Knight in <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſhire; and for Conſcience ſake Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, at that Juncture, when I might have had an 100 and 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> by the year. <hi>Burmingham</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter</hi> was offered me, and many other Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which I all refuſed; and by Faith, caſt my ſelf on the bare Providence of God near this twenty years: I have been in <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and <hi>Worceſter</hi> Goals, for the Teſtimony of my Conſcience, and for preaching the Goſpel, I have taken the Oath of Supremacy, in the Senſe it was given out by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as may be teſtified in the County of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and have ſince preached up and down in many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>England,</hi> and ſometimes taught Children for my Lively-hood, and to maintain my Wife and Children, having a Wife and three Children now alive, in <hi>Oxford</hi>-ſhire. 3. My coming up to <hi>London</hi> was providentially: the laſt year, I preached at <hi>Bednal Green</hi> at Mr. <hi>Howels</hi> Meeting, and many times at Mr. <hi>Sharps</hi> in <hi>Beech</hi> Lane at the Morning Lecture there, before divers Miniſters, and by name Mr. <hi>Franklin,</hi> and was never attainted for Jeſuitiſm, or Popery, or any other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. At <hi>Michaelmas</hi> I went in the Country, and Mr. <hi>Farrington</hi> by one Mr. <hi>Million</hi> wrote three Letters for me, to come and aſſiſt him, and promiſed me a Comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maintenance; I left a good School then, and came up near the end of <hi>October,</hi> 1679. We drew Articles to this Purpoſe, and ſealed them, and he promiſed me that Quarter, and told me, it would be ten Pounds he did believe, but I received at <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> 3 pound odd Money, that was all I ever had upon the Account of him, and have in Purſuance of the Articles, preached ſince the laſt Quarter, except a little time I was in the Country, for Nothing; and when I came up again to <hi>L.</hi> Mr. <hi>Farrington</hi> told me the Houſe was taken over his Head by one Mr. <hi>Streaton,</hi> and that yet he had ſo far prevailed with the Landlords, that if he could produce a Years Rent aforehand, he yet ſhould have the houſe, and told me, I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit 25 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> of it. and then I ſhould go Partners with him; I told him, that I had no money, and was poor, and If I had, I would not lay it down ſo, and that by Articles I was to have half this Quarter, and ſo on without medling with the Rent,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45624:5"/>he replied, that the Articles were worth nothing in Law; and then I began to ſmell him out, and told him, then I hoped to have the Benefit of it as well as he, ſo we parted about the beginning of <hi>April</hi> 1680. the next day being <hi>Tueſday,</hi> at nine of the Clock at Night, I being ſick a bed, Mr. <hi>Farington</hi> ſent one Mr. <hi>Forreſt</hi> for me to come to Mr. <hi>Stretton</hi> and him, at the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Cheeſe in <hi>New Market.</hi> I told him I could not then, and it was not a fit time, if I had been well, the Gentleman told me that Mr. <hi>Stretton</hi> told Mr. <hi>Far.</hi> that he had not taken the Houſe, but becauſe he brought me in there. I deſired him to tell Mr. <hi>Far.</hi> before Mr. <hi>Stretton,</hi> that I would have him diſcharge me, that he might come to no more Damage by me, and that Mr. <hi>Stretton</hi> accuſed me of ſlandering him. I ſaid to <hi>Mr. Forreſt,</hi> and prayed him to tell <hi>Mr. Stretton,</hi> that what I ſaid in the Publick place, of him, was by <hi>Mr. Faringtons</hi> Order, or elſe I ſhould not have preached that day; and that I would at any other time meet <hi>Mr. Stretton,</hi> and ſatisfie him, but he never ſent for me yet. But it was reported at <hi>Mr. Farrington</hi>'s Meeting, that a Coach came for me to come to <hi>Mr. Jenkins, Mr. Baxter,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Turner,</hi> but I refuſed; which Lie I believe, came from that corrupt Fountain, that once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in publick, that he was given to lying and Covetouſneſs; which both my Purſe and Body have been very ſenſible of this 16 weaks; well I ſent on <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following to <hi>Mr. Farington</hi> to know if I ſhould continue Preaching with him, he ſent me Anſwer, that he would excuſe me, he would do it himſelf, ſince which, I have preached in <hi>Compton</hi> Street, and do intend to continue God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and never move to trouble <hi>Mr. Farington,</hi> and am ſorry I have ever. Upon this little Storm, I was to be metamorphoſied into a Jeſuit (by whoſe Malice and Subtilty I leave to God) as <hi>Acteon</hi> was into a Stag, that I might be hunted to Death, out of their way; and being one Lords day by Providence called to preach in <hi>Southwark</hi> to one Mr. <hi>Madocks</hi> an honeſt ſober Gentleman, as far as I know, where I preached upon the Sacrament, and in his hearing and the reſt, neither aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Conſubſtantiation with the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or Tranſubſtantiation with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which I ſuppoſe no Jeſuit in the World would deny, if he ſhould preach upon it. Yet for all this, this Monſter of a Jeſuit muſt be brought forth, like <hi>Aarons</hi> gol-Calf, caſt into the fiery Paſſions of ſome ſelf-ended Zealots, and there came out the Jeſuit; this Gentleman Mr. <hi>Madocks</hi> being as I was informed, at the Spittle at Dr. <hi>Ainſloes</hi> Synod, there came the Jeſuit out. I will not ſay it was formed in that Claſs, but Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Vincent</hi> a Gentleman, to me a Stranger, contrary to the Law and Rules of Charity there publickly (the Act ſmelling a little of Envy for Intereſts ſake) traduced him for letting a Jeſuit preach, and that he was like to be as bad, for ſo doing, nor would his honeſt Teſtimony of my Doctrine, quench their Flames, but in all Haſt I muſt come and appear before Mr. <hi>V.</hi> or I know not whom, and truly, had Mr. <hi>V.</hi> been ſo Civil as to have ſent me word to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, though it had been a little magiſterical and prelatical, Before he had Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitized me, and traduced <hi>Mr. Maddocks;</hi> truly I would have gone upon my Hands. But after he had done me all the Wrong he could, then I ſuppoſed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45624:5"/>way of Vindication more pleaſing to me, than to proſtrate to Self and Pride, and thorow Evil to bring out Good: but theſe men are more verſed in the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian</hi> Law to hang a man and then Judge him, than in the Laws of the pure Love of Chriſt, and this by my own Experience I have found. And now they have brought an imaginary Jeſuit, out of the Chymeraes of their own Brains; we want Judicious Moſes to grind him to Powder, and caſt him into the Waters of Oblivion; but I heartily wiſh, that none of the fond Founders of <hi>this Jeſuit,</hi> be forced to drink in all their Potions, the Powder of <hi>this Jeſuit,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> did of their Golden Calf: and I wiſh a little time do not manifeſt it. The next thing is my Book, <hi>Libella ſua &amp; fata habebant,</hi> muſt come under the Severity of their laſhing Cenſures, whereas I hear five Objections are made againſt it, beſide that I did not come to ask their Maſter-ſhips Leave to do it. 1. That about Gods laying Iniquity it ſelf upon Chriſt. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.12.13.14.15. of my Book. God imputes to Believers Chriſts Righteouſneſs, and his Holineſs alſo. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.12. and 10.14. for their Juſtification and <hi>per contra</hi> imputed to him our Sins and Impieties, and then is the Church without Spot and Blemiſh before God. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26.27. compared with <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7. and <hi>Numb.</hi> the 23.21. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.7.10, 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. and conſult Doctor <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Sermons upon the 53. <hi>Iſa.</hi> The next Objection is, That I affirm that Faith, Repentance, and new Obedience, are not Conditions of our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that being freely by Grace, but Fruits and Effects of it. When their Worſhips ſhall pleaſe to anſwer my Book, I ſhall (God willing) have in Readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a Reply to anſwer this and other Objections, fully to the Satisfaction of the honeſt humble Soul. The next Objection is about the perſonal Reign of Chriſt, whom I affirm will with his Saints reign in Perſon, over the Kingdoms of this World, and that at the end of the <hi>Roman,</hi> or 4. Monarchy, and that at the end of the little Horn, that ſhall of all the ten wear out the Saints, Chriſt ſhall come in the Clouds, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.17.18.21, 22.25, 26, 27. verſe <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.20.21. Whom the Heavens muſt contain till the Reſtitution of all things. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or till the time that all things that now ſeem fallen and dead, ſhall again ſtand on its Legs. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. the twenty four Elders, the dead Saints of old and new Teſtament muſt reign upon Earth, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World ſhall be delivered to Chriſt and them. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.6.7. and then the Miſtery ſhall be finiſhed that is not yet. For all theſe Gent. think that they have all the Truth in the World, like <hi>Homers</hi> Illiads in a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell, in their Fiſts—but <hi>Haud parum falluntur,</hi> and when Mr. <hi>B.</hi> for ſo Mr. <hi>Farington</hi> told me, that he ſaid it was Popery to hold the perſonal Reign. I ſay when he, with all his Logick and Sophiſtry, and School Diſtinctions, hath anſwered Dr. <hi>Homes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mead,</hi> Dr. <hi>Twiſs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Durant,</hi> and others: and plainly from Gods word proved it to be Popery, then will I bethink me to be of another Mind.—The next Objection is <hi>pag.</hi> 135. and <hi>pag.</hi> 136. where firſt I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45624:6"/>deſire the Nonconformiſts to ſubmit to the King of Heaven and his Decrees, for according to that, ſhall the Decrees of earthly Monarchs be diſpenſed, and to think no Evil of the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, though the Parliament do not ſit; and that his Majeſty gave us our Liberty when the Parliament abridged it. I heartily pray that the King and his Parliament may propitiouſly agree: but I am thankful for my Liberty, and deſire to be obedient in all things wherein I ought, and leave the Event and Succeſs to the Lord, and to the Prince, whom he hath ſet upon the Throne; and I hope this is no Token of a Jeſuitical Spirit. And <hi>pag.</hi> 136. I bewailed the bitterneſs of our Spirits one againſt another, delivering my Judgment according to my Experience, for this dozen years; and when I ſee it better, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is more indiſſimulate Love, affectionate Bowels, Charity to the Poor, and leſs of Reſpect of Perſons, <hi>James</hi> 2. to their gold fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered and gliſtering profeſſing Gallants, for their outward Bravery; when I ſay, I ſee it amended, and men of differing Judgments tender, humble, and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Envy to them they dogmatize not with, I ſhall change my Sentiment, and ſing <hi>Te Deum</hi> for Joy, but the Proverb is, Touch a gald Horſe and he will wince.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, my Non-appearance before the Miniſters. 1. I affirm that no Miniſter did ever as I know of, ſend directly for me, nor come to me, except <hi>Mr. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,</hi> and (as his Meſſenger <hi>Mr. Forreſt</hi> ſaid) <hi>Mr. Stretton,</hi> to an Alehouſe at nine of the Clock at Night in <hi>New-Market,</hi> when I was ſick in Bed. And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another time, there came a Gentleman to my Lodging, one Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> a Coach-harneſs-maker in Princes ſtreet, puffing and huffing at me, who a little before, had committed my Book to the Flames, to ſhew his Teeth againſt the Truths of Chriſt, which he in Scorn called Hereſie, and me a Papiſt, being himſelf both ignorant of the Truth and of Popery, he charged me then that I ſaid Chriſt was filthy—let all ſober Perſons judge that, if in my Book ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is—but we may ſay, Chriſt was guilty, becauſe our Guilt was impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, ſo he was a Sinner, and the greateſt Sinner ſaid <hi>Luther,</hi> becauſe our Sins was imputed to him, ſo was our Filth too; the while he is ſtill perſonally and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herently pure, and we filthy and guilty too in that Senſe: but if Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> will needs have the Filth of his Sin to reſt upon himſelf, and be imputed to himſelf, till the Spirit hath cleanſed him from the Filth in the Sight of God for his Juſtification (an Office which the Scripture no where gives to the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. it being peculiar to Chriſts Blood. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9) My An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to him and his Maſter <hi>Mr. Lob</hi> is, let him that is filthy be filthy ſtill. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. and he that is made Righteous and Holy by Chriſts imputed Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.11, 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. And alſo his Guilt and Filth imputed to Chriſt, when on the Croſs. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. let him (yea he will) be Holy and Righteous ſtill. I wiſh Mr. <hi>Lob</hi> to teach his Diſciples Humanity, for they pretend to ſo much Divinity, that they forget their Humanity, for Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> told me peremptorily before <hi>Mrs. Sarah Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45624:6"/>and <hi>Mrs. Allice Porter,</hi> that he was a better man than I, and when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, who the Miniſters were that I muſt meet and where, he told me he ſcorned to give me an account, then I bid him go and bid his Maſters ſend a wiſer Meſſenger; beſides many other Incivilities that he offered me, before theſe forementioned Perſons, at my Lodging, and then went, as ſoon as he had done, and told Lies on me to excuſe his own Incivility and Inhumanity: I wiſh Mr. <hi>Lob.</hi> by tranſmuting the two laſt Letters of his Name from <hi>Lob</hi> to <hi>Lag.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which in <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſignifies a Flagon, may be ſo full of Goſpel Wine, not Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, Malice and Envy; that all his Diſciples may drink out of him, ſuch Goſpel Truths, as may better inable them to talk of and diſcern the Truths of the Goſpel, than to burn mens Books without Authority, and abuſe their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But I deſire the mighty Lord to change and forgive them, and to convert us all from <hi>Lob</hi> to <hi>Leb,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Caleb,</hi> a good Heart.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Mr. Farrington</hi> told <hi>Mr. Forreſt,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Forreſt, Mr. Paſham,</hi> that if I did not come before the Miniſters, they would have a Warrant, and bring me for a Jeſuit before the King and Councel, and that I was of no Univerſity, but bred up beyond Seas, and had Ordination there. I thank <hi>Mr. Farrington,</hi> this is my Reward for preaching for him to uphold his Meeting this 3 Months for nothing; and ſuppoſe I were of no other Univerſity than <hi>Kederminſter-ſtuff:</hi> Why may not I preach for all that as well as he?</p>
            <p>If any object, why I meddle with <hi>Mr. Baxter,</hi> I anſwer, I honour <hi>Mr. Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Perſon, Worth, and Parts, but do not love his Principles. And I am but of the Opinion of ſome great Divines in <hi>England;</hi> whom <hi>Mr. Baxter</hi> was pleaſed to tax with Anti-nominaniſm, that he with his great and prodigious Parts, hath one time with another, done the Church more Hurt than Good, ſee <hi>Mr. Edw. Bagſhaw</hi> againſt him, and ſee that Diſcourſe of that Reverend Divine, Dr. <hi>O.</hi> in his <hi>Append.</hi> in the end of that worthy Piece againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2. I anſwer, <hi>Mr. Farinton</hi> told me, that <hi>Mr. Stretton</hi> told him, that <hi>Mr. Baxter</hi> would anſwer my Book, and that it was damn'd Hereſie; and that the Title of the Anſwer was, <hi>A warning to the World, how and who they hear.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have but anticipated Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and deſire the World, and the Saints, and Believers in the World, that value their Souls, and the Truth of their Faith and Principles, to take Heed how they read his Books, in which there is ſprinkled here and there, ſuch Doctrine as may be read in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and other Popiſh Authors. See Dr. <hi>Willets</hi> Synop. againſt Popery, and Dr. <hi>White</hi> againſt <hi>Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the Jeſuit, and <hi>Jewel</hi> againſt <hi>Hardin,</hi> and compare them with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> and other Books, and his <hi>Call to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted,</hi> where I muſt tell him, I do not believe, that by that Book, one Sinner is truly turned to Chriſt, and the true Faith of him. And if any of theſe Goſpel Miniſters, ſo called, will ſhew me their Authority from Chriſt, and the Magiſtrate, to command my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance before their Synods and Claſſes, or their Power to catechiſe or exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45624:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>me, I will come with Cap in hand and bended Knees, but till then they muſt excuſe me. And if any Chriſtian or Miniſter without diſſimulate Love, for brotherly Conference, come to me, or at Conveniency deſire my Company, I ſhall not refuſe it.—And if any object, theſe are Lies put on <hi>Mr. Baxter</hi> and others; I anſwer, it muſt then be from Mr. <hi>Farrington,</hi> who is a Miniſter of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Ordination, though I cannot tell of what Univerſity, and who ſhall I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, if not a Miniſter. And laſtly, if any man would hear or diſcern my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, they may come any Lords day to <hi>Mr. Bartons</hi> in <hi>Compton</hi> ſtreet, <hi>they ſhall be welcome; at the Weſt end of</hi> Monmouth-ſtreet <hi>near the white Hart.</hi> My Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is, The great God grant his Majeſty's Life long in the Land, the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Liberty, Truths, Propagation, and Chriſts Glory and perſonal Reign and Coming. I for my part am but the pooreſt and weakeſt of Chriſts Royal Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, and walk daily depending on him for Strength, fearing to fall; but if I ſhould fall into that Damnable, Debauched, Curſed, Helliſh, Swiniſh Beaſtly Sin of Whoredome, and Drunkenneſs, Lying and Covetouſneſs, deceit and Craft, to uphold my Luſt and Intereſt, Pride and Wantonneſs, and ſhould go about with other mens Works and Doctrine, to preach up Love to cloak my Luſts; Let then the Miniſters, and Church, and People of Chriſt, except by unfeigned Repentance I ſubmit and reform, for ever refuſe me, ſilence me, and baniſh me their Society, and that, they that then follow me, (though they profeſs never ſo fair) would be as bad as I,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHRIES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the Reader, line 15. for <hi>and to,</hi> r. <hi>and into.</hi> l. 18. for <hi>this individual</hi> r. <hi>his individual.</hi> p. 2. for <hi>deripiunt</hi> r. <hi>decipiunt.</hi> p. 6. l. 18. r. 16 Weeks. p. 3. l. 2. for <hi>the redeemer</hi> r. he redeemed and.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45624:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
